[MUSIC]
[出版偏誤]
In this lecture we'll talk
about publication bias.
這一講來談「出版偏誤」
You would hope that researchers publish
all data that they collect regardless of
無論研究者收集的資料是否支持假設
身為讀者都希望能看到全部的訊息
whether their results
are statistically significant and
無論研究者收集的資料是否支持假設
身為讀者都希望能看到全部的訊息
supporting their hypothesis or not.
無論研究者收集的資料是否支持假設
身為讀者都希望能看到全部的訊息
It turns out that this is not the case and
if you do research,
然而實際情況並不是如此
如果你正在進行某種研究
it's important to recognize
publication bias in the literature.
必須認識存在於浩瀚文獻裡的出版偏誤
Now one of the biggest problems
of the over reliance on p-values
造成出版偏誤的最大原因是科學界過度依賴以p值決定論文是否值得刊登
in the scientific literature,
is their use as a threshold to publish.
造成出版偏誤的最大原因是科學界過度依賴以p值決定論文是否值得刊登
People think that if a p-value
is smaller than 0.05,
很多評審覺得只要研究結果的p值小於0.05，那麼這個結果就值得刊登
the results are worthwhile
to be published.
很多評審覺得只要研究結果的p值小於0.05，那麼這個結果就值得刊登
But if the result is higher than 0.05,
如果結果是大於0.05，通常都建議不值得刊登
they often do not submit these papers for
publication.
如果結果是大於0.05，通常都建議不值得刊登
As a consequence,
如此長久運作下來
if we plot the p-value distribution in
the scientific literature, we can see that
把大量文獻的p值集合起來繪圖，就會看到這條之前曾解釋過的奇特曲線
there's sort of a curve going on as
we explained in previous lectures.
把大量文獻的p值集合起來繪圖，就會看到這條之前曾解釋過的奇特曲線
You can see it here by the red line,
the red curve is illustrating this.
也就是這張圖裡的紅色曲線
And then at the threshold of 0.05, the
vertical red line, we can see a huge drop.
從橫軸標示0.05的地方，畫一條垂直線
會看到一個巨大落差
You might think that this curve should
continue on, and it should, but
理論上紅色曲線應該與每一個柱子的頂端相接
what's indicated here is a large missing
section of the scientific literature.
這個落差顯示有一大塊應該存在的文獻並未浮出枱面
It's like a big monster came by and
彷彿有隻怪獸把這些大於0.05的文獻都吃掉了
bit part out of all the p-values
that should be there.
彷彿有隻怪獸把這些大於0.05的文獻都吃掉了
So this missing part is missing
due to publication bias.
這缺掉的一大塊就是出版偏誤所造成
There are studies but
we just don't have access to it.
而且這些遺缺的研究很難重見天日
In the scientific literature,
this is known as the file drawer problem.
這種現象被稱為抽屜問題(file drawer problem)
If people perform a study and they observe
a non-significant result, a p-value
很多研究者只要發現統計結果得到大於0.05的p值
higher than 0.05, they're less likely
to submit this result for publication.
傾向不發表這些結果
Instead, they store the data
in their file drawer.
這些結果最後只能在某位研究者的抽屜裡沉眠
Nowadays, this probably would be
a folder on your computer somewhere.
資訊發達的今天應該說被隱藏在某份硬碟裡
Now, as a consequence,
if you look at the published literature,
這個問題導致看到的文獻幾乎都是支持某種假設
most of the published results
confirm the hypothesis.
這個問題導致看到的文獻幾乎都是支持某種假設
So, in psychology, more than 90% of
以心理學來說，超過90%的論文支持作者想檢驗的假設
published papers support the hypothesis
that they set out to test.
以心理學來說，超過90%的論文支持作者想檢驗的假設
Some people have even joked that if we're
so good at predicting what will happen,
有人開玩笑說如果每個心理學家都能準確預測結果
why do we bother collecting data anyway?
幹嘛還要辛苦地收集資料
If 90% of the studies that we
perform support the hypothesis,
既然有90%的心理學研究都支持假設
then let's just skip
the data collection and
只要有好主意必定有資料支持
assume that whenever we have a good idea
it actually is supported by the data.
何必再去設計研究收集資料？
Now, of course, this can't be the truth,
this is not what's going on.
當然這是玩笑話，任何人都不可能這麼做
We just don't have access to all
the non-significant results and
90%的現象是因為不顯著與不支持假設的結果都被隱藏起來了
all the results that do not
support the hypothesis.
90%的現象是因為不顯著與不支持假設的結果都被隱藏起來了
There's some reasons why people are
hesitant to submit non-significant results
研究者不想把不顯著的結果發表出來是有理由的
for publication.
Null-results are difficult to interpret.
主要是無差異的結果很難做推論
It might be that there's just no effect.
這種結果可能是確實不存在預期的效果
It's also possible that the study you
designed simply wasn't very good.
或許是現在的設計還不夠好
Maybe there is a true effect, but
you need to study it in a better way.
導致雖然存在真實效果，卻無法偵測出來
You need to change your study design.
因此必須更改設計
Now, we see that people might try
again and again, and of course,
很多研究者會不斷的嘗試
if you take this to the extreme and
you only submit for publication
最極端的情況是從20次實驗結果裡拿最顯著的那1次結果去發表
the one significant result out of 20
different tries to observe something.
最極端的情況是從20次實驗結果裡拿最顯著的那1次結果去發表
In this extreme situation, you're only
publishing null results, false positives.
這種情況就造成文獻裡出現了偽陽性的報告
Now there is random variation
in studies we perform.
我們都曉得只要是實徵研究必定存在隨機變異
We know this.
This is a good example
of what it can lead to.
這個咖啡究竟會致癌還是防癌的研究是個好例子
If we publish results, then sometimes
there will be an extreme finding that
這類研究有顯示支持咖啡能預防癌症的報告
shows a very strong positive effect.
Sometimes there will be a finding that
shows a very strong negative effect.
也有顯示咖啡會導致癌症的報告
As long as we publish all available
evidence, we can do a meta analysis that
只要對所有報告做個整合性分析
says, on average there's
really nothing going on here.
就會看到平均來說咖啡不防癌也不致癌
But because we only publish
these extreme findings,
如果只有其中一方的報告能被刊登
significant results in either direction,
you end up with a scientific literature
讀過所有論文後，每個讀者都會認為咖啡致癌或防癌是事實
where everything both causes cancer and
prevents cancer.
讀過所有論文後，每個讀者都會認為咖啡致癌或防癌是事實
So, let's say that you study
the amount of wine that you drink and
把研究題目換成飲酒導致癌症的風險評估
the likelihood that you will get cancer.
There will be a study that says,
there's a strong positive association.
肯定有研究表示兩者有強烈的正相關
If you drink more wine you
are more likely to get cancer.
也就是喝越多酒越有可能得到癌症
There will also be studies that say,
也肯定有研究得到另一種結果
if you drink more wine you're
less likely to get cancer.
喝多少和致癌的風險無關
All in all, there's just nothing going on,
but people are just publishing flukes,
總結來說，即使沒有存在任何可能性，隨機變異會導致偏向某一邊的報告出現
false positives, on either side.
And if we would have access to the entire
literature which you could just say this
遍覽所有相關文獻才能排除隨機變異，確認有沒有真實效果
is just a null effect,
there's just random variation around zero.
遍覽所有相關文獻才能排除隨機變異，確認有沒有真實效果
Now, as long as a research area
doesn't share all results,
只要某個研究領域不分享所有結果，就無法成為真正的量化實證科學
it's not a quantitative science.
This is a strong statement, but really, if
you want to express the evidence that's in
這是立場強烈的主張。實際上如果無法讓所有人獲得完整的資料
the data,
you need to have access to all the data.
很難說服任何人，有充分的證據支持你的假設
If you only have a subset of
all the available evidence,
只呈現一部分的證據
you cannot make a good statement
about what's going on.
無法斷言相關研究能否獲得一致結果
So if you want to be a quantitative
science, you need to publish all data.
好的實徵科學研究者必須呈現所有可信的資料
There are some recent initiatives where
people try to convince researchers to
這些措施能幫助研究者自主呈現不顯著的資料
empty their file drawers.
These are online databases where people
can report previously unpublished results,
像是透過雲端平台公開未發表的不顯著結果
often non-significant findings, so
that the scientific community has access
to all the data that has been collected.
讓所有研究者都能取得全部的資料
Now it's important to realize that
there can be over 200 published
務必切記，即使你發表超過兩百篇有顯著結果的報告
studies with significant p-values
without there being a true effect.
這些報告宣誠的效果有可能並不真實
As long as there are thousands of people
examining the same research question, and
除非是上百位研究者一起檢視同一個問題
all these researchers perform
multiple studies a year,
並且同一年裡進行研究
then after a couple of years we'll
have ended up with a literature that
幾內之年就會出現一批文獻讓讀者確認是否存在偽陽性問題
contains exclusively false positives.
Of course, this is a very extreme
situation but it might happen.
當然，這是最理想但是有可能達到的境界
Now publication bias cannot be
corrected in a meta analysis, but
整合性分析不可能修正出版偏誤，但是能偵測它
it can be detected.
So you can see that it's present and
as a consequence,
無論整合性分析顯現相關研究的出版偏誤有多高
whenever publication bias is
present in a meta analysis,
只要有呈現，就必須小心地推論整體效果量的意義
be more careful in interpreting
the meta analytic effect size estimate.
只要有呈現，就必須小心地推論整體效果量的意義
In this graph,
we see what's known as a funnel plot.
這張圖是所謂的漏斗圖(funnel plot)
We have simulated a large
number of studies where the two
這是模擬一批效果量有0.66的相關研究在漏斗圖的分佈
effect size of a Cohen's d of 0.66.
We see a vertical dotted line
at the true effect size and
圖中的垂直線就在真實效果0.66的所在
all the individual studies fall more or
less around this true effect.
所有相關研究均勻分佈在真實效果的兩側
On the vertical axis,
we see the standard error.
左側的縱軸的數值代表標準誤(SE)
You can think of this as the sample size.
可以直接想成是樣本數(SE = SD/sqrt(N))
The further we go up in the graph,
the bigger the sample size becomes and
因為標準誤越小，樣本數就越大
at the bottom we have studies
with very small sample sizes.
越接近圖底部的資料點樣本數越少
Now, the gray pyramids indicates the area
灰色三角區域表示出現在這裡的資料點都沒有達到統計顯著水準
within which studies are not
statistically significant.
灰色三角區域表示出現在這裡的資料點都沒有達到統計顯著水準
If a dot falls in the white area it
will be statistically significant,
落在白色區域的資料點才有達到起碼0.05的統計顯著水準
p-value smaller than 0.05.
But if it falls within the gray pyramid,
it's not statistically significant.
但是與灰色重疊的區域不能說達到充分的統計顯著
Now in these simulated studies,
the pattern is exactly as you would expect
這張模擬圖顯示一系列有真實效果且無出版偏誤的研究該有的樣子
if there's a true effect and
no publication bias.
這張模擬圖顯示一系列有真實效果且無出版偏誤的研究該有的樣子
But let's take a look at the meta analysis
where the meta analytic effect size was
但是如果有真實效果卻有出版偏誤的研究會是什麼樣子？
exactly the same but
where publication bias is present.
但是如果有真實效果卻有出版偏誤的研究會是什麼樣子？
This data comes from a real
meta analysis by Hagger et al,
這張圖是2010年Hagger等人分析自我耗損(ego depletion)相關研究的結果
2010, examining ego depletion.
We see that the dots
are distributed in a peculiar way.
資料點呈現一種奇特的分佈
They fall very close on
the edge of the gray pyramid.
所有資料沿著灰色區域邊緣分佈
It's almost like people were throwing
these dots from the side against the gray
如果這是箭靶，好像有人瞄準灰色旁邊的白色區域射箭一樣
pyramid and
they stuck exactly on the border.
如果這是箭靶，好像有人瞄準灰色旁邊的白色區域射箭一樣
Of course, there is still some variation
around it but there is really a surprising
雖然有些資料點遠離灰色區域邊緣
number of p-values or
studies very close to this border.
集中趨勢依然令人無法忽視
This is an illustration
of publication bias.
這也是讓出版偏誤現形的一種方式
There's some selection going on.
有些人為因素讓這類研究傾向報告顯著結果
We're missing studies that should
fall within the gray pyramid and
灰色區域有一部分應該出現的研究並未現世
a lot of these studies are just only
on the border of the funnel plot.
讓這塊主題的多數研究結果集中在區域邊緣
Now as I said, we cannot correct for
bias but we can detect publication bias.
就像稍早說的，我們只能偵測出版偏誤卻不能修正它
One of the tests that we can do
is a trim and fill analysis.
有一種偵測方法是刮補式分析(trim and fill)
The basic idea here is that there
are certain studies that are missing and
背後的想法是假設有一些研究確實「被消失」
we can fill in these missing
studies based on some assumptions.
根據假設補上可能被消失的資料
So in this case, we see a lot of open
circles which are studies that are assumed
圖中的白圏圈就是假設被消失的資料
to exist and are filled in in
the existing meta analysis.
補上後再做一次整合性分析
Now trim and fill analysis will
give you an adjusted effect size.
這樣就會得到一個校正後的效果量估計
But it's very tricky to interpret this.
但是根據校正後的效果量推論要小心
It's probably not correct,
the adjustment might not be enough, so
校正的假設可能是錯誤的，有可能是白費功夫
you can use the trim and
fill analysis to say look.
最多只能說校正結果僅供參考
There is bias in this meta analysis, but
這樣的整合性分析已存在偏誤
you cannot use the adjusted
effect size estimate as
修正的效果量不能當成沒有被出版偏誤影響的真實效果
an indication of what the true effect size
is if there would not have been biased.
修正的效果量不能當成沒有被出版偏誤影響的真實效果
Another way to take a look at what the
true effect size removing any bias might
還有一種檢測真實效果的方法是只看大樣本的資料
be is by only taking a look
at the biggest studies.
還有一種檢測真實效果的方法是只看大樣本的資料
This is called a cumulative meta analysis.
這種方法稱為累進式整合性分析
You start with the biggest study that you
have available in your set of studies in
從手邊有最大樣本的研究開始計算初始效果量
the meta analysis, and
you calculate the effect size and
接著加入第二大的研究計算效果量
then you add the second biggest,
the third biggest etc.
再依此類推做到最後一項研究
And you only look at the effect size
estimate after adding a number of really
以最後得到的效果量對評估真實效果
large studies.
Now, in this plot,
這張圖從上往下看
you can see that there is a slightly
changing effect size estimate.
會發現效果量的估計逐步改變
It becomes bigger, and bigger, and
bigger, as the studies become smaller.
隨著樣本數較少的研究加入，效果量越來越大
Now, this is problematic.
然而這裡有個問題
Ideally, we would see that
the largest studies all, sort of,
理論上應論看到樣本數最大的研究
(最上面的水平線)
center around the true effect size.
應該涵蓋真實的效果量
(最下面的水平線)
But, even in this case,
in this literature of Eagle depletion,
在這個同樣是自我耗損的例子裡
the largest studies
already contain some bias.
樣本數最大的研究也存在某種偏誤
Another technique you see in
the published literature to detect bias,
還有一種偵測出版偏誤的技術叫做「失效安全指數」(Failsafe N)
is known as Failsafe N.
It calculates how many studies you need,
with no true effect,
這是表示如果真實效果不存在，在整合性分析效果量達到0之前，
還需要填入多少研究資料
before the meta-analytic effect
size is reduced to zero.
這是表示如果真實效果不存在，在整合性分析效果量達到0之前，
還需要填入多少研究資料
It's a little bit of a peculiar
measure and even the person
這個指數的發明者坦承有些尚未克服的計算問題
所以不推薦研究者使用它
who originally came up with it,
no longer recommends people to use it.
這個指數的發明者坦承有些尚未克服的計算問題
所以不推薦研究者使用它
So don't use this in
your own meta analysis.
所以請勿在整合性分析使用這個指數
More fruitful approach
might be meta-regression.
另一種更具彈性的方式是整合性迴歸分析(meta-regression)
In meta-regression you
draw a regression line
這種方法是為納入分析的所有資料繪製迴歸線
through the studies in your meta analysis.
If you think about the funnel plot we
saw earlier, it's basically a regression
稍早提到的漏斗圖就是一種迴歸分析
line where instead of each
individual being a data point,
把原本每個代表p值的點
now each study is
an individual data point.
換成每個研究的統計值
You can use the end point of the
regression line where the standard error
以迴歸線與偏準誤為0交會的統計值，做為真實效果量的估計
is zero to estimate the true effect size.
Even though bias is present.
儘管還是有偏誤存在
Now, use these techniques with care but
techniques such as Egger's regression
謹慎運用這類方法，像是Egger氏迴歸
might give you an indication of the true
effect size after correcting for bias.
也許能獲得校正偏誤之後的真實效果量
Of course,
we already talked about p-curve analysis.
當然也可以運用第五週提到的p-Curve分析
You can compliment your traditional meta
analysis and the bias detecting techniques
結合傳統的整合式分析與偏誤偵測技術
such as meta-regression or trim and
fill with a p-curve analysis.
像是前面提到的整合式迴歸與刮補分析於p-Curve
If the p-curve analysis says that
there is evidential failure, and
如果p-Curve顯示支持有真實效果的研究總體證據力僅勉強達標
(圖中的綠色線)
the bias correcting techniques all show
that after correcting for bias there's
校正偏誤之後顯示可能存在真實效果
reason to assume there's still a true
effect, then you might conclude that
校正偏誤之後顯示可能存在真實效果
the available evidence is quite
reliable and supporting the hypothesis.
可以推論現有的證據有一定的可信度
Let's assume you perform
a set of four studies.
假想現在有四項獨立研究
Each study has 80% power
which is quite reasonable.
每個研究都有至少80%的統計考驗力
Then in this case,
the probability of observing exclusively
所有研究都會出現顯著結果的機率是0.8的四次方
也就是41%
significant results is 0.8 x
0.8 x 0.8 x 0.8 which is 41%.
所有研究都會出現顯著結果的機率是0.8的四次方
也就是41%
So if you perform four studies
with 80% power in each study,
也就是說如果一項實驗在維持80%考驗力的情況下
the probability of finding exclusively
significant results is only 41%.
分別進行四次獨立研究，
只有41%的可能性獲得全部都是顯著的結果
So most four study papers with 80%
power should have at least one or
四次之中至少有一次或二次出現不顯著的結果
two non significant results.
So given that non significant
studies should be expected,
如果應該有不顯著的結果出現
why don't you just publish
them when they happen?
為何不將它放在論文裡發表？
One way to publish results regardless of
their significance level is of course
一種不管結果是否顯著都可以發表的方式就是「註冊研究」
if you preregister them.
If you decide that the study is worthwhile
to do and the reviewers agree, then they
只要研究計畫有價值且同行審查也同意
will give you an in principle acceptance
after reviewing your study design.
未執行的設計就能原則性接受(in principle acceptance)
If you follow up with the plan and
you perform the study as detailed,
只要依照被接受的計畫執行研究內容
then you can publish the results
regardless of the significance level and
不管結果有沒有顯著都可以正式發表
prevent publication bias.
全面避免出版偏誤
There are now some journals that
accept pre-registered reports.
有的期刊開始接受刊登註冊研究報告
Comprehensive Results in
Social Psychology is one.
例如「可理解的社會心理學研究結果」(Comprehensive Results in
Social Psychology)
Cortex is another journal
that very early started with
腦皮質(Cortex)是最早開始接受註冊研究報告的期刊
accepting preregistered reports.
And if you're collecting data
that's very difficult to collect,
如果正在進行的研究資料很難收集
it's a lot of hard work, and
you really want this data to reach
很難達到統計顯著卻有科學價值
the scientific literature you can
consider submitting to these journals.
不妨考慮投稿這類期刊
Now if you perform a set of studies and
如果手上的研究出現了不顯著的結果
you observe some non-significant
results that you decide are not
如果手上的研究出現了不顯著的結果
worthwhile to really discuss
in detail in the methods and
但是不方便在方法或結果的段落裡討論
results section, then at the very least
discuss these results in the discussion.
最好在論文最後的討論段落中提及
This is really the place to say, these
are some other studies that we've tried.
這個部分最適合說明曾經嘗試的其它研究
We did not observe anything, but we think
we have very good reasons why we're
特別是解釋為何不呈現沒有特別發現的資料
ignoring this data because
whatever the reason is.
特別是解釋為何不呈現沒有特別發現的資料
If you've discussed them, share the data,
make it available online.
討論並公開分享這些資料
Let people draw their own conclusions.
讓讀者自行判斷
In this lecture, we've talked about
publication bias and how to detect it.
這一講介紹什麼是出版偏誤與偵測的方法
I really think that publication
bias is one of the biggest
個人認為出版偏誤是今天所有科學研究者要嚴肅面對的挑戰
challenges that the scientific community
needs to address in the next few years.
個人認為出版偏誤是今天所有科學研究者要嚴肅面對的挑戰
As long as there is
strong publication bias,
只要有明顯的出版偏誤存在
it's impossible to have
a quantitative science,
量化科學研究就不會產生任何價值
so if we decide to fix one thing in
science it should really be this.
要修補它就要用科學的態度面對它
[MUSIC]
[課程結束]